Finding Aid for American Friends Service Committee. Michigan Area Office records, 1956-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- National and Regional Offices
  - Dayton Regional office
    - 1968-1984
      - Open Doors to the Third World (speakers program) 1976-1977 (Box 16)
      - Orientation to American Friends Service Committee circa 1980-1981 (Box 16)
      - Personnel Committee
        - Evaluation of Personnel Committee 1985 (Box 16)
        - Joyner, Brenda 1978 (Box 16)
      - Program Contracts 1977 (Box 16)
      - Program Evaluations 1978 (Box 16)
      - Program Report 1971-1972 (Box 16)
      - Publications (Newsletters; includes "Changing Times," and "Peace Action") 1976-1978 (Box 16)
      - Regional Peace Education Committee Minutes 1975-1983 (partial) (Box 16)
      - Staff Meeting Minutes
        - November 1983 (Box 16)
        - March 1984 (Box 16)
      - Staff Reports 1969-1983, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Third World Intern Proposal 1976-1977 (Box 16)
      - Youth Education Action 1969-1973 (Box 16)
      - Vietnam Food Program 1977 (Box 16)
  - Great Lakes Region (GLR)
    - General (Box 17)
    - Annual Retreat 1985 (Box 17)
    - Communications Program (Box 17)
    - Executive Committee Meetings
      - April 1987 (Box 17)
      - June 1987 (Box 17)
    - Meeting on Using Volunteers November 1984 (Box 17)
    - Minutes and related meeting materials including memos and correspondence
      - 1985 (Box 17)
        (includes Annual Meeting notes)
      - 1986 (Box 17)
      - 1987, 2 folders (Box 17)
        (includes AFSC Sourcebook on Rural Justice & the Farm Crisis)
      - 1988, 3 folders (Box 17)
      - 1989, 3 folders (Box 17)
      - 1990, 2 folders (Box 17)
      - 1991, 2 folders (Box 17)
      - 1992, 2 folders (Box 17)
      - 1993 (Box 17)
      - 1994-1997 (scattered) (Box 17)
    - Staff Consultative Group May 1986 (Box 17)
    - Staff Retreat 1987 (Box 17)
  - Regional Coordinating Team
    - Minutes and related materials 1985-1993, 7 folders (Box 17)
    - Lake Erie Yearly Meeting, 2 folders
      - 1978-1980 scattered (Box 17)
      - 1991 (Box 17)
  - Michigan and Northern Ohio Coordinating Committee (MANOCC) (Box 18)
    - Minutes and related materials 1989-1991, 8 folders (Box 18)
  - Midwest Regional Office, Gay and Lesbian Task Force 1981-1984 (Box 18)
  - Chicago Regional office (Box 18)
  - Northeast Ohio office
    - General (Box 18)
    - Northeast Ohio Peace and Justice Calendar (Box 18)
- Administrative files (Michigan Area Office)
  The MAO administrative series includes a chronological subseries dating from 1956 to 1987. These files consist of miscellaneous reports, memoranda, and published material not easily associated with other series. Other files concern the deliberations of the personnel committee. Researchers may find the personnel files of the Michigan Area Office especially helpful; staff members periodically evaluated MAO programs, and these evaluations were included in the personnel files. There are also mailings files which are a helpful complement to other sets of records, especially as they often contain minutes and staff reports.
  - General chronological file: reports, memoranda, etc.
    - Undated 1956-1973, 25 folders (Box 18)
    - 1974-1980, 31 folders (Box 19)
    - 1981-1987 1992, 8 folders (Box 20)
  - Personnel Committee
    - General, 9 folders (Box 20)
    - Minutes 1974-1976, 1979-1982, 5 folders (Box 20)
    - Correspondence 1975-1977 (Box 20)
    - Evaluations 1975-1976 (Box 20)
    - Staff Meetings
      - Minutes 1975-1977 (Box 20)
      - Feedback 1975-1976 (Box 20)
    - Staff and Committee Correspondence 1975-1977 (Box 20)
    - Nominating Committee
      - (For 1975-1976) 1975 (Box 20)
      - (For 1977-1978) 1977 (Box 20)
    - Orientation 1975-1978 (Box 20)
  - Personnel
    - Employee Files
      - King, Karen 1980 (Box 20)
      - Tate, Nancy 1982-1983 (Box 20)
      - Volk, Joe 1978-1981 (Box 20)
    - Job Descriptions circa 1978-1984 (Box 20)
    - Job Inquiries 1978-1980 (Box 20)
    - Nominating Committee 1974, 1978-1980, 4 folders (Box 20)
  - General Topical
    - Affirmative Action Consultation 1980 (Box 20)
    - American Friends Service Committee Family Camp 1973 (Box 20)
    - Ann Arbor Friends Directory and Bulletin 1974 (Box 20)
    - Annual Report 1985-1986 (Box 20)
      (entitled, Communications Record for the Michigan AFSC)
    - Budget information 1981, 1995 (scattered) (Box 20)
    - Committee Calendar 1980-1981 (Box 20)
    - Committee Lists 1973-1982 (Box 20)
    - Green Pastures Regional Organization 1973-1979 (Box 20)
    - Mailings 1972-1973, 1977-1983, 18 folders (Box 21)
    - Michigan Area Office Annual Meeting, Catherine Shaw's Talk 1980 (Box 21)
    - Mission Statements 1986 (Box 21)
    - Organizational Documents 1970-1987 (Box 21)
    - Program Secretary's Monthly Reports 1972-1973 (Box 21)
    - Publicity/Releases
      - 1978-1979 (Box 21)
      - 1981 (Box 21)
      - Clippings 1975-1976 (Box 21)
      - Biographies prepared for news releases (of Lou Schneider and Jim Powell) (Box 21)
    - Restructure Subcommittee 1977 (Box 21)
    - Staff Meeting Minutes October 1973-September 1975 (Box 21)
    - Staff Reports (scattered) 1992-1995 (Box 21)
- Topical files
  The Topical Files series relate to miscellaneous topics of concern both locally and nationally, primarily in the 1960s and 1970s. There is, for example, some materials relating to the MAO's participation in the Del Monte Boycott of 1977, in the Detroit Anti-Hunger Program of 1976-1977, and in the Telephone Tax Resistance movement in 1970. In the late 1960s and early 1970s, MAO was active in draft counseling activities. Included in this series is correspondence of the organization with young men in Michigan concerning the draft and conscientious objection to war. The letters reflect the thinking of a large number of American youth who were apprehensive about the war in Vietnam and who sought to resist the draft or to find alternative service.
  - Michigan Area Office circa 1966-1977
    - American Friends Service Committee 50th anniversary, Detroit 1967 (Box 21)
    - Boycott of Del Monte 1977 (Box 21)
    - Comprehensive Employment Training Act Proposals, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Detroit Anti-Hunger Program 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Draft advisees (correspondence with), 9 folders (Box 21)
    - Draft Centers
      - Publicity (Box 22)
      - Out-of-state (Box 22)
      - Detroit and environs, Ann Arbor (Box 22)
      - Flint, Saginaw, Bay City, Midland area (Box 22)
      - Middle Michigan (Lansing and Jackson) (Box 22)
      - Northern Michigan (Box 22)
      - Western Michigan (Box 22)
    - Native-American Project 1978, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Telephone Tax Resistance 1970 (Box 22)
    - Western Michigan Program
      - General, 5 folders (Box 22)
      - Native American Task Force (Box 22)
      - Jamaica Seminar 1979 (Box 22)
      - Minutes 1973-1977 (Box 22)
      - Program Secretary's Report 1973-1977 (Box 22)
      - Monthly Reports 1972-1977 (Box 22)
      - Michigan Personnel and Guidance Association--Counter Recruiting 1974-1976 (Box 22)
      - Women's Program 1976 (Box 22)
      - Moment for a New Society (Macroanalysis) 1974-1975 (Box 22)
      - United Campaign 1975-1976 (Box 22)
      - Hunger Program 1974-1975 (Box 22)
      - Amnesty (Box 22)
  - National, regional, and area offices circa 1966-1987
    - AIDS-Related Communication Coalition (ARCC) Meetings October 1986-June 1987, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - Alternative Service and Conscientious Objectors (Box 22)
    - Correspondence with Department of Political Science, University of Georgia (Box 22)
    - Counter-Recruitment (Box 22)
    - Detroit School of Missions (Box 22)
    - Draft Counseling, 7 folders (Box 22)
    - Draft Repeal, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - Draft Resistance, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - History -- AFSC History in Michigan (Box 22)
    - Midwest Committee for Draft Counseling (Box 22)
    - Midwest Regional School of Missions (Box 22)
    - Military Counseling (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous Friends Literature (Box 23)
    - Ohio Council of Churches (Box 23)
    - Pacifism (Box 23)
    - Peace Organizations (Box 23)
    - Peace Conversion Task Force (Box 23)
    - Police Spying in Michigan (Red Squad)
      - Correspondence 1977-1983 (Box 23)
      - Police Files, Copies
        - American Friends Service Committee circa 1963-1975, 2 folders (Box 23)
        - Hefley, Ted 1962-1970 (Box 23)
        - Stevens, Janet and Daniel 1959-1961 (Box 23)
    - Southeast Asia (Box 23)
    - Southern Africa, 4 folders (Box 23)
    - Southern Africa Letter 1980 (Box 23)
    - Vocations for Social Change (Box 23)
    - Vieques (Caribbean Island) 1981-1982 (Box 23)
    - Women Under Apartheid ("Women in Defiance: The Southern African Experience" conference at the University of Michigan) April 1983 (Box 23)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  Audio-Visual Materials series includes a scattering of photos and some audio-cassettes. The Photographs include black and white contact prints documenting many conferences in the early 1980s; descriptive lists accompany the sheets. The next folder contains many black and white photographs and contact prints documenting the Royal Oak Township Weekend Workcamp of April 1964. These photographs are unidentified otherwise. The final folder contains undated black and white photographs taken at the Washtenaw County Jail. The audio cassettes relate to the issue of racism and homophobia.
  - Photographs
    - Photographs primarily of speakers and audience at 50th anniversary conference held in Detroit in 1967 (Box 23)
    - Contact Prints from Conferences, early 1980s (Box 23)
    - Royal Oak Township Weekend Workcamp April 1964 (Box 23)
    - Washtenaw Jail, late 1970s (Box 23)
  - Audio tapes
    - Interviews and training material mainly relating to topic of Homosexuality
      - PJ Two Ravens and Trans Panel (Box 23)
      - Interview with Ulrika Persson 1992 (Box 23)
      - Fran Myer, part 1 and 2, 2 audiocassettes (Box 23)
      - Racism is a Violation of Human Rights 1994 (Box 23)
      - The Church's Understanding of Homosexuality, Rev. Bill Hybels 1993 (Box 23)
      - Toward Understanding Training 1997 (Box 23)
  - Posters
    - Anti-war, 75th anniversary, etc. posters (Folder Ba)